Byzantine Institute, Inc. Dumbarton Oaks Research Library and Collection. The Byzantine Institute and Dumbarton Oaks Fieldwork Records and Papers, ca. late 1920s-2000s: Finding Aid
Image Collections and Fieldwork Archives, Dumbarton Oaks Research Library and Collection
- Administrative Records, 1920s - 2000s, MS.BZ.004-01; 28 boxes including 333 folders
  - Correspondence, ca. 1920s - 2000s, MS.BZ.004-01-01; 20 boxes including 280 folders
    - Correspondence, ca. 1940s - 1950s, MS.BZ.004-01-01-02; 2 boxes including 29 folders
      - Correspondence from Thomas Whittemore to Paul Sachs, April 15, 1943, MS.BZ.004-01-01-02-019; 1 folder; Box 2 contains letters regarding the restoration and conservation of Hagia Sophia and Kariye Camii. They document: research activities, artifact purchases, film and photographic documentation, scaffolding plans, administrative and personnel matters following Whittemore’s death, grant and permit proposals, and official permits.
        Sachs, Paul, 1878-1965
      - Correspondence between John Thacher, Thomas Whittemore, Seth Gano, Persis Mason, and Vladimir Rayevsky, April 1943 – August 1951, MS.BZ.004-01-01-02-020; 1 folder; Box 2 contains letters regarding the restoration and conservation of Hagia Sophia and Kariye Camii. They document: research activities, artifact purchases, film and photographic documentation, scaffolding plans, administrative and personnel matters following Whittemore’s death, grant and permit proposals, and official permits.
        Refers to acquisitions by Dumbarton Oaks from the Byzantine Institute (“Coptic textile” and “Coptic tympanum and angel”; microfilm copies of the Byzantinische Zeitschrift vol. 1941-1942; the Byzantine collection (e.g., archaeological books, photographs, and manuscripts) of Hayford Peirce; and work on Byzantine churches in Istanbul.
        Persis W. Mason was born in Boston on April 25, 1916, daughter of Herbert and Persis Furbish Mason, Persis worked in the Dumbarton Oaks Research Library 1941-1946, following brief employment at Harvard's Fogg Art Museum after graduation.
        Vladimir N. Rayevsky was possibly the Secretary of the Byzantine Institute Library in Paris
        Mason, Persis W., 1916-2004
        Rayevsky, Vladimir N.
        Peirce, Hayford, 1883-1946
        Byzantinische Zeitschrift, 1892-
      - Report and correspondence with the British Council of the British Embassy in Ankara, David Russell of the Walker Trust, and the Department of Antiquities in Jerusalem, March – July 1945, MS.BZ.004-01-01-02-021; 1 folder; Box 2 contains letters regarding the restoration and conservation of Hagia Sophia and Kariye Camii. They document: research activities, artifact purchases, film and photographic documentation, scaffolding plans, administrative and personnel matters following Whittemore’s death, grant and permit proposals, and official permits.
        Suggestions and plans for the restoration and excavations around the Sultan Ahmed Mosque in Istanbul by the Walker Trust. Also includes a letter from Steven Runciman and a report by Oliver Davies.
        Steven Runciman was an English historian of the Byzantine Empire and the Crusades
        Oliver Davies was a British archaeologist
        Israel Antiquities Authority, 1948-
        Runciman, Steven, 1903-2000
        Davies, Oliver, 1905-1986
      - Correspondence between Thomas Whittemore and Seth Gano, 1945 – August 1948, MS.BZ.004-01-01-02-022; 1 folder; Box 2 contains letters regarding the restoration and conservation of Hagia Sophia and Kariye Camii. They document: research activities, artifact purchases, film and photographic documentation, scaffolding plans, administrative and personnel matters following Whittemore’s death, grant and permit proposals, and official permits.
        Proposal to establish an American School of Archaeology in Turkey and ideas for an Archaeological Park in Istanbul.
        Archaeological Institute of America, 1879-
      - Correspondence between the Society for the Promotion of Byzantine and Modern Greek Studies and the Byzantine Institute, 1946 – 1948, MS.BZ.004-01-01-02-023; 1 folder; Box 2 contains letters regarding the restoration and conservation of Hagia Sophia and Kariye Camii. They document: research activities, artifact purchases, film and photographic documentation, scaffolding plans, administrative and personnel matters following Whittemore’s death, grant and permit proposals, and official permits.
        Notes on the publication of "Byzantion", American series 1940-1945, and "Byzantina-Metabyzantina".
        The Society for the Promotion of Byzantine and Modern Greek Studies was the publisher of Byzantine Metabyzantina
        Society for the Promotion of Byzantine and Modern Greek Studies
      - Correspondence between the Medieval Academy of America and the Byzantine Institute, October 1946 – April 1951, MS.BZ.004-01-01-02-024; 1 folder; Box 2 contains letters regarding the restoration and conservation of Hagia Sophia and Kariye Camii. They document: research activities, artifact purchases, film and photographic documentation, scaffolding plans, administrative and personnel matters following Whittemore’s death, grant and permit proposals, and official permits.
        Concerning Kenneth M. Settons, "The Catalan Domination of Athens 1311-1388".
        Medieval Academy of America, 1925-
        Setton, Kenneth M., 1914-1995
      - Correspondence between the Eastman Kodak Company, the Byzantine Institute (e.g., Thomas Whittemore), and J.G. Saltzman Inc., January 1947 – May 1951, MS.BZ.004-01-01-02-025; 1 folder; Box 2 contains letters regarding the restoration and conservation of Hagia Sophia and Kariye Camii. They document: research activities, artifact purchases, film and photographic documentation, scaffolding plans, administrative and personnel matters following Whittemore’s death, grant and permit proposals, and official permits.
        J.G. Saltzman Inc. was a photographic and lighting equipment company on Lexington Avenue in New York.
        Eastman Kodak Company, 1888-
        J.G. Saltzman Inc.
      - Correspondence between the American Council of Learned Societies and the Byzantine Institute, January 1947 – May 1952, MS.BZ.004-01-01-02-026; 1 folder; Box 2 contains letters regarding the restoration and conservation of Hagia Sophia and Kariye Camii. They document: research activities, artifact purchases, film and photographic documentation, scaffolding plans, administrative and personnel matters following Whittemore’s death, grant and permit proposals, and official permits.
        Refers to the publications “Eastern Elements of Western Chant” by Egon Wellesz and “Twenty Canons of the Trinity Hirmologium” by H.J.W. Tillyard, both publications of "Monumenta musicae Byzantinae." Also includes Whittemore’s request for two Fulbright Fellowships for George Holt and John Howard Lee to assist in the uncovering and conservation work at St. Irene in Istanbul.
        American Council of Learned Societies, 1919-
        Holt, George
        Lee, John Howard, 1922-1980
        Wellesz, Egon, 1885-1974
        Tillyard, H. J. W., 1881-1968
      - Correspondence with Seth Gano, August 1947 – March 1953, MS.BZ.004-01-01-02-027; 1 folder; Box 2 contains letters regarding the restoration and conservation of Hagia Sophia and Kariye Camii. They document: research activities, artifact purchases, film and photographic documentation, scaffolding plans, administrative and personnel matters following Whittemore’s death, grant and permit proposals, and official permits.
        Refers to "The Bulletin of the Byzantine Institute" and Alison Frantz's publications on the Athenian Agora.
        Frantz, Alison, 1903-1995
      - Obituary of Nicholas Kluge, October 5, 1947, MS.BZ.004-01-01-02-028; 1 folder; Box 2 contains letters regarding the restoration and conservation of Hagia Sophia and Kariye Camii. They document: research activities, artifact purchases, film and photographic documentation, scaffolding plans, administrative and personnel matters following Whittemore’s death, grant and permit proposals, and official permits.
      - Correspondence between the Ministry of Education in Turkey and the Byzantine Institute (e.g. Boris Ermoloff and Thomas Whittemore), April – June 1948, MS.BZ.004-01-01-02-029; 1 folder; For related materials, see Subgroup 1, Box 10.; Box 2 contains letters regarding the restoration and conservation of Hagia Sophia and Kariye Camii. They document: research activities, artifact purchases, film and photographic documentation, scaffolding plans, administrative and personnel matters following Whittemore’s death, grant and permit proposals, and official permits.
        Refers to the restoration of Saint Irene, which was supported by the Ministry of Education in Turkey.
        Ministry of National Education, Turkey, 1920-
        For related materials, see Box 11.
      - Correspondence with Seth Gano, May 1948 – April 1950, MS.BZ.004-01-01-02-030; 1 folder; Box 2 contains letters regarding the restoration and conservation of Hagia Sophia and Kariye Camii. They document: research activities, artifact purchases, film and photographic documentation, scaffolding plans, administrative and personnel matters following Whittemore’s death, grant and permit proposals, and official permits.
        Relates to a proposal to establish the American Research Center in Egypt.
      - Correspondence between Boris Ermoloff, Seth Gano, and Thomas Whittemore, May 1948-May 1951, MS.BZ.004-01-01-02-031; 1 folder; Box 2 contains letters regarding the restoration and conservation of Hagia Sophia and Kariye Camii. They document: research activities, artifact purchases, film and photographic documentation, scaffolding plans, administrative and personnel matters following Whittemore’s death, grant and permit proposals, and official permits.
        Refers to an Album of Photographs of Saint Sophia.
      - Correspondence from Ernest Hawkins to Boris Ermoloff, November 14, 1948, MS.BZ.004-01-01-02-032; 1 folder; Box 2 contains letters regarding the restoration and conservation of Hagia Sophia and Kariye Camii. They document: research activities, artifact purchases, film and photographic documentation, scaffolding plans, administrative and personnel matters following Whittemore’s death, grant and permit proposals, and official permits.
        Relates to the termination of projects in Hagia Sophia and Kariye Camii.
        Ernest Hawkins was a Byzantinist and a mosaics conservator. He joined the Byzantine Institute in 1938, assisting Thomas Whittemore and leading the field team that restored the mosaics at Hagia Sophia. Field Director for the Byzantine Institute and Dumbarton Oaks. After Whittemore's death, Hawkins worked for Paul Underwood, eventually becoming Field Director and Research Associate at Dumbarton Oaks. A conservative restorer, Hawkins never repainted or altered mosaics, and preferred to leave them in their original positions rather than resetting them. He published extensively in the Dumbarton Oaks Papers and was married to Hilda Routen.
        Hawkins, Ernest J.W., 1905-1993
      - Correspondence between John Thacher and Paul Underwood, Bulk: 1952-19541948 – 1955, MS.BZ.004-01-01-02-033; 1 folder; Box 3 contains correspondence documenting the fieldwork activities in Kariye Camii. Also includes newspaper clippings, records of financial expenses and personnel matters, and administrative records regarding the future of the Byzantine Institute and the publication of an issue of Life magazine, which featured the restoration and conservation work in Hagia Sophia.
        Contains memos and reports regarding the history of the Byzantine Institute and state of monuments in Turkey.
        Paul A. Underwood was an American archaeologist and art historian. A Byzantinist and Dumbarton Oaks Scholar, he began his career at Princeton. He undertook a study of the decoration sources of the Church of the Holy Apostles with Albert Friend in 1945. After Thomas Whittemore's death in 1950, Underwood became the Field Director of the Byzantine Institute. He completed Whittemore's Hagia Sophia work and then supervised the excavation work at Kariye Djami. In 1960, he became a full professor at Dumbarton Oaks. Six years later, Underwood published his Istanbul research in the three-volume "The Kariye Djami." He died shortly after editing the fourth volume.
        Underwood, Paul A., 1902-1968
      - Correspondence between Paul Underwood and William MacDonald, Bulk: July 1950-October 19551948 - January 1958, MS.BZ.004-01-01-02-034; 1 folder; Box 3 contains correspondence documenting the fieldwork activities in Kariye Camii. Also includes newspaper clippings, records of financial expenses and personnel matters, and administrative records regarding the future of the Byzantine Institute and the publication of an issue of Life magazine, which featured the restoration and conservation work in Hagia Sophia.
        Reports on work progress and condition of Kariye Camii and financial statements on work in Istanbul.
        William MacDonald was American architectural historian of classical Rome. MacDonald participated in the Byzantine Institute's uncovering of mosaics at Hagia Sophia in the early 1950s.
        MacDonald, William, 1921-2010
      - Correspondence between Daniel Webster and Seth Gano, March – April 1949, MS.BZ.004-01-01-02-035; 1 folder; Box 3 contains correspondence documenting the fieldwork activities in Kariye Camii. Also includes newspaper clippings, records of financial expenses and personnel matters, and administrative records regarding the future of the Byzantine Institute and the publication of an issue of Life magazine, which featured the restoration and conservation work in Hagia Sophia.
        Refers to Mosaic tracings and prints.
        Daniel G. Webster was an employee of the Photographic Service Department of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT), ca. late 1940s.
        Webster, Daniel G.
      - Correspondence between Life magazine and the Byzantine Institute, May 1949 – July 1951, MS.BZ.004-01-01-02-036; 1 folder; Box 3 contains correspondence documenting the fieldwork activities in Kariye Camii. Also includes newspaper clippings, records of financial expenses and personnel matters, and administrative records regarding the future of the Byzantine Institute and the publication of an issue of Life magazine, which featured the restoration and conservation work in Hagia Sophia.
        Relates to photographs of the Byzantine Institute in Hagia Sophia taken by Dmitri Kessel for Life magazine.
        Life Magazine, 1883-
        Kessel, Dmitri, 1902-1995
        For a copy of the Life Magazine issue, refer to Subgroup I, Series IV: Publication Materials. For copies of the photographs, see The Thomas Whittemore Papers, ca. 1875-1966, in the Image Collections and Fieldwork Archives, Dumbarton Oaks, Washington, D.C. http://www.doaks.org/library-archives/icfa/icfa_pdfs/doaks-icfa-whittemore-papers-findingaid.pdf
      - Correspondence between the Byzantine Institute (e.g., Thomas Whittemore, Seth Gano, and William MacDonald), September 1949 – December 1954, MS.BZ.004-01-01-02-037; 1 folder; Box 3 contains correspondence documenting the fieldwork activities in Kariye Camii. Also includes newspaper clippings, records of financial expenses and personnel matters, and administrative records regarding the future of the Byzantine Institute and the publication of an issue of Life magazine, which featured the restoration and conservation work in Hagia Sophia.
        Relates to the director position following Thomas Whittemore’s death.
      - Correspondence between Edward W. Forbes and the Byzantine Institute (e.g., Sterling Dow, Seth Gano, and Boris Ermoloff), October 1949 – June 1950, MS.BZ.004-01-01-02-038; 1 folder; Box 3 contains correspondence documenting the fieldwork activities in Kariye Camii. Also includes newspaper clippings, records of financial expenses and personnel matters, and administrative records regarding the future of the Byzantine Institute and the publication of an issue of Life magazine, which featured the restoration and conservation work in Hagia Sophia.
        Relates to the transition of the Byzantine Institute following Thomas Whittemore’s death.
        Dow, Sterling, 1903-1995
      - Correspondence between Carsten Høeg, Columbia University Press, and the Byzantine Institute (e.g., Sterling Dow and William MacDonald), November 1949 – June 1951, MS.BZ.004-01-01-02-039; 1 folder; Box 3 contains correspondence documenting the fieldwork activities in Kariye Camii. Also includes newspaper clippings, records of financial expenses and personnel matters, and administrative records regarding the future of the Byzantine Institute and the publication of an issue of Life magazine, which featured the restoration and conservation work in Hagia Sophia.
        Refers to the following publications: “La musique byzantine chez les Slaves, Bulgares et Russes, du IXe au XIVe siècle” by R. Palikarova-Verdeil and “Twenty Canons of the Trinity Hirmologium” by Henry Julius Wetenhall Tillyard in Monumenta musicae Byzantinae.
        Carsten Høeg was a Danish classical philologist and founding director of the series Monumenta Musicae Byzantinae.
        Høeg, Carsten, 1896-1961
        Palikarova-Verdeil, R., 1904-1960
      - Correspondence between the Oxford University Press, H.J.W. Tillyard, and the Byzantine Institute (e.g., William MacDonald), November 1949 – April 1953, MS.BZ.004-01-01-02-040/041; 2 folders; Box 3 contains correspondence documenting the fieldwork activities in Kariye Camii. Also includes newspaper clippings, records of financial expenses and personnel matters, and administrative records regarding the future of the Byzantine Institute and the publication of an issue of Life magazine, which featured the restoration and conservation work in Hagia Sophia.
        The first folder contains correspondence that refers to the publication: “Twenty Canons from the Trinity Hirmologium” by Henry Julius Wetenhall Tillyard in Monumenta musicae Byzantinae
        H. J. W. Tillyard was a scholar and specialist in Byzantine music
        Oxford University Press, 1478-
      - Correspondence from Egon Wellesz to Thomas Whittemore, December 1949 – April 1950, MS.BZ.004-01-01-02-042; 1 folder; Box 3 contains correspondence documenting the fieldwork activities in Kariye Camii. Also includes newspaper clippings, records of financial expenses and personnel matters, and administrative records regarding the future of the Byzantine Institute and the publication of an issue of Life magazine, which featured the restoration and conservation work in Hagia Sophia.
        Egon Wellesz was an Austrian-born British composer, teacher and musicologist specializing in Byzantine music.
    - Correspondence, ca. 1950s, MS.BZ.004-01-01-03; 2 boxes including 36 folders
      The first box contains correspondence documenting the transition of the Byzantine Institute upon the death of Thomas Whittemore and Paul Underwood’s appointment as the new Field Director.
      - Brief report on the work conducted at Kariye Camii, 1949, MS.BZ.004-01-01-03-043; 1 folder; Box 4 contains correspondence documenting the transition of the Byzantine Institute upon the death of Thomas Whittemore and Paul Underwood’s appointment as the new Field Director.
      - Correspondence between the U.S. Department of State and the Byzantine Institute (e.g., Thomas Whittemore, Robert P. Blake, and Seth Gano), January – June 1950, MS.BZ.004-01-01-03-044; 1 folder; Box 4 contains correspondence documenting the transition of the Byzantine Institute upon the death of Thomas Whittemore and Paul Underwood’s appointment as the new Field Director.
        Relates to Joseph C. Grew’s involvement with the conservation and restoration of Hagia Sophia, Whittemore’s death, and the plan to continue the Byzantine Institute fieldwork projects.
        U.S. Department of State, 1789-
        Blake, Robert Pierpont, 1886-1950
        Grew, Joseph Clark, 1880-1965
      - Correspondence between the U.S. Department of State, the National Museum of Istanbul, and the Byzantine Institute, January – November 1950, MS.BZ.004-01-01-03-045; 1 folder; Box 4 contains correspondence documenting the transition of the Byzantine Institute upon the death of Thomas Whittemore and Paul Underwood’s appointment as the new Field Director.
        Relates to Fulbright scholarships in Turkey
        Istanbul Archaeological Museums, 1869-
      - Correspondence between the Seattle Art Museum and Thomas Whittemore, February 1950, MS.BZ.004-01-01-03-046; 1 folder; Box 4 contains correspondence documenting the transition of the Byzantine Institute upon the death of Thomas Whittemore and Paul Underwood’s appointment as the new Field Director.
        Refers to Whittemore’s request to include a reproduction of the Zoe mosaic panel from Hagia Sophia in the collections of the Seattle Art Museum
        Seattle Art Museum, 1906-
      - Correspondence between The Pierpont Morgan Library and Thomas Whittemore, February – May 1950, MS.BZ.004-01-01-03-047; 1 folder; Box 4 contains correspondence documenting the transition of the Byzantine Institute upon the death of Thomas Whittemore and Paul Underwood’s appointment as the new Field Director.
        Relates to an article for the "Liber Amicorum" by Thomas Whittemore
        Pierpont Morgan Library, 1890-
      - Correspondence between The Metropolitan Museum of Art and Thomas Whittemore, February 1950 – June 1951, MS.BZ.004-01-01-03-048; 1 folder; Box 4 contains correspondence documenting the transition of the Byzantine Institute upon the death of Thomas Whittemore and Paul Underwood’s appointment as the new Field Director.
        Refers to six (6) silver objects that were sent to the Metropolitan Museum of Art for examination and the return of a reproduction of the Deësis mosaic panel from Hagia Sophia to the museum
        Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1866-
      - Correspondence between the Archbishop of the Greek Orthodox Church of North and South America and John Thacher, February 1950 – October 1967Bulk: February 1950-February 1957, MS.BZ.004-01-01-03-049; 1 folder; Box 4 contains correspondence documenting the transition of the Byzantine Institute upon the death of Thomas Whittemore and Paul Underwood’s appointment as the new Field Director.
        Archbishop Michael was Primate of the Greek Orthodox Church of North and South America from 1949-1958
        Michael, Archbishop, 1892-1958
      - Correspondence from John Nicholas Brown to the Ministry of Education in Turkey, March – August 1950, MS.BZ.004-01-01-03-050; 1 folder; Box 4 contains correspondence documenting the transition of the Byzantine Institute upon the death of Thomas Whittemore and Paul Underwood’s appointment as the new Field Director.
        Includes a pamphlet entitled Kemal Ataturk: An Appreciation
        John Nicholas Brown was born in New York in 1900. His father and uncle died shortly after his birth, causing the press to dub him "the richest baby in America." He attended Harvard and studied the History and Literature of Classical Cultures, traveling extensively after graduation. Always interested in historical architecture and art, he founded the Medieval Academy of America and was on the Byzantine Institute Committee. His public life included stints as the head of the Rhode Island division of the Public Works Administration, and Assistant Secretary of the Navy for Air from 1946-1949. He was married to the reporter Anne Seddon Kinsolving and had three children.
        Brown, John Nicholas, 1900-1979